Finding Aid for Josephine Fellows Gomon papers, 1913-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Josephine Fellows Gomon papers 1913-1975
Gomon, Josephine Fellows, 1892-1975.
85710 Aa 2; AC
Executive secretary to Detroit Mayor Frank Murphy, 1930-1933, chairwoman of the Mayor's Unemployment Committee, later director of the Detroit Housing Commission, candidate for Detroit public office, and director of women personnel at the Willow Run Bomber Plant during World War II. Correspondence and diaries concerning the Murphy mayoralty, Clarence Darrow and the Ossian Sweet Murder Trial of 1925, and local Detroit politics; and photographs.
10 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Josephine Gomon (Donor No. 5511 ) in several installments beginning in 1974. Additional donations have since been made by family members.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Josephine Fellows Gomon was born in Ann Arbor of Mary Walsh and Augustus W. Fellows and lived there until 1913, when she graduated from the University of Michigan with a degree in mathematics. She taught mathematics and physics at the College of the City of Detroit, now Wayne State University. In 1916, she married R. Louis Gomon, a University of Michigan engineering graduate. They had five children, including Bobby Lou (Mrs. Frederick Dewey); William; Howard Garner, who was killed in World War II; Jeanne (Mrs. Guy Nunn); and R. Louis, Jr. While raising her family, Mrs. Gomon taught throughout the Detroit public school system, wrote a child education column for The Detroit News, and worked for the local Planned Parenthood league.
In the 1920s, Mrs. Gomon met Clarence Darrow, and their friendship continued throughout the Ossian Sweet trial in Detroit and up until the time of his death. The Recorders Court Judge who presided over that trial was Frank Murphy, who was also a graduate of the University of Michigan. In 1930, Mrs. Gomon worked on Murphy's campaign for mayor of Detroit and upon his election to that office became his executive secretary and chaired the Mayor's Unemployment Committee.
When Murphy went to the Philippines in 1933, Mrs. Gomon was appointed the director of the newly established Detroit Housing Commission by Acting Mayor John Smith. Brewster and Parkside Houses were built during her term in office. She left that position in 1938, and worked in private business until 1941, when she was appointed by Harry Bennett of the Ford Motor Company as Director of Women Personnel at the newly constructed Willow Run bomber plant. In this capacity she fought for industrial safety, day care centers, and helped in the planning and construction of war workers' housing. In 1929, 1935, and 1941, Mrs. Gomon ran for elective office in the city of Detroit, the first election for the Board of Education and the other two for Common Council. Although she met defeat in every campaign, she received substantial electoral support throughout the city and was one of the first women to run for public office in Detroit.
From 1945 to 1948, she conducted a radio program on WKMH called "Opinion Unlimited." In 1948, her husband, R. Louis Gomon, died. Until her death in 1975, Mrs. Gomon participated in campaigns for social welfare and human rights through her memberships in the Americans for Democratic Action, NAACP, and the American Civil Liberties Union.
In 1960, she was honored at a tribute dinner which was attended by nearly every well-known political and governmental figures in the state of Michigan. A year later, Wayne State University gave Mrs. Gomon an honorary degree commemorating her long years of service to the city and the state.
In her later years, Mrs. Gomon attempted to write two major works. The first was a biography of Frank Murphy. The second project dealt with Henry Ford and Harry Bennett.
The Josephine Gomon papers have been divided into the following series: Correspondence; Clippings/Scrapbooks; Notebooks of news items; Diaries; Biographical/Personal; Materials concerning Frank Murphy; Materials related to Gomon's projected biography of Frank Murphy; Ford Motor Company materials; Photographs.
Subjects:
Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938.; Depressions--1929--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.). Housing Commission.; Detroit (Mich.). Mayor.; Detroit (Mich.). Mayor's Unemployment Relief Committee.; Gomon, Josephine Fellows, 1892-1975.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Sweet, Ossian, 1895-1960.; Willow Run Bomber Plant.; Women in politics--Michigan.; World War, 1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Michigan.; Banquets.; Bennett, Harry Herbert, 1892-1979.; Coughlin, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1891-1979.; Crowds.; Detroit (Mich.)--Mayors.; Detroit (Mich.)--1935.; Dwellings--Michigan--Harbor Beach.; Gomon, Josephine Fellows, 1892-1975.; Governors--Michigan.; Harbor Beach (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Horseback riding.; Housing.; Mayors--Michigan--Detroit.; Michigan. Legislature.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Political elections.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Smoking.; Women--Political life.
Contributors:
Arnow, Harriette Louisa Simpson, 1908-1986.; Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1889-1968.; Bowles, George Edward, 1915-; Brickley, James E., 1927-; Bumgardner, Eleanor M. (Eleanor Margaret); Carey, Ed.; Cavanagh, Jerome Patrick, 1928-1979.; Downs, Tom, 1916-; Edwards, George, 1914-; Ferency, Zolton A., 1922-1993; FitzGerald, Frank.; Girardin, Ray, d. 1971.; Griffin, Robert P. (Robert Paul), 1923-2015; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Knight, John Shively, 1894-1981.; McNamara, Patrick Vincent, 1894-1966.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Murphy, George, 1897-1961.; Ravitz, Mel, 1924-; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; Riegle, Donald W., 1938-; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Romney, Lenore LaFount.; Souris, Theodore, 1925-; Staebler, Neil, 1905-2000; Sugar, Maurice, 1891-1974.; Taylor, Hobart, 1920-1981.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Woodcock, Leonard.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  Mrs. Gomon's correspondence is very rich. The World War II period is particularly well documented by a series of almost daily letters written by Mrs. Gomon to her children. The letters of Mrs. Gomon's son-in-law, Guy Nunn, are also very informative about the situation in post-World War II Germany and the V.F.W. in the early 1950s.
  - By date
    - 1915-1945 undated, 51 folders (Box 1)
    - 1946-1965, 55 folders (Box 2)
    - 1966-1971, 46 folders (Box 3)
    - 1972-1975, 14 folders (Box 4)
  - By name
    - Cline, Leonard 1920s (Box 4)
    - Moody, Blair 1930s (Box 4)
    - Prevost, Cliff 1930s (Box 4)
- Clippings/Scrapbooks
  The scrapbooks represent a very useful collection of newspaper clippings dealing with public housing in Detroit between 1933 and 1937 and, again, are particularly useful because no published indexes are available for the papers clipped.
  - 1930-1975 undated, 17 folders (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks 1933-1937 primarily relating to public housing in Detroit (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbooks 1933-1937 primarily relating to public housing in Detroit (Volume 2)
    (continued)
- Notebooks of news items
  Mrs. Gomon took extensive notes on a variety of subjects that interested her. The notebooks she kept on various newspapers reporting about political and social events are particularly valuable since the newspapers in question are, with the exception of the New York Times, not indexed.
  - Detroit News
    - 1910 (Box 4)
      (Mayoral election)
    - 1920 (Box 4)
      (Recorders' Court, Edward J. Jeffries, Sr.)
    - 1921 (Box 4)
    - January 1923-March 1923 (Box 4)
      ("Big Four" election, cont.)
    - July-December 1923 (Box 4)
    - December 1923-February 1924 (Box 4)
    - January-July 1924 (Box 4)
    - November 1924 (Box 4)
    - January-November 1925 (Box 4)
      (Ossian Sweet case)
    - November 1925-May 1926 (Box 4)
    - September 1929-January 1930 (Box 4)
    - January 1930 (Box 4)
    - February-April 1930 (Box 4)
    - April-June 1930 (Box 4)
    - May-August 1930 (Box 4)
      (Bowles recall; Buckley murder)
    - June 1930-February 1931, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - February 1931-March 1937, 20 folders (Box 5)
      (lacking 1934-1935)
  - Detroit Times
    - January 1923-June 1932, 22 folders (Box 5)
      (July-September 1923 notebook includes March 1937)
    - June 1932-January 1937, 4 folders (Box 6)
      (lacking May 1933-August 1936; December 1936 notebook includes Detroit News, March 1933)
  - Detroit Free Press
    - March-July 1930 (Box 6)
    - September-October 1930 (Box 6)
    - 1937 (Box 6)
    - May 1937 (Box 6)
  - Manila Bulletin, April-June 1933 (Box 6)
  - Manila Tribune
    - February 1933-June 1936, 6 folders (Box 6)
      (lacking December 1934-January 1936)
  - New York Times
    - 1930 (Box 6)
    - February-March 1937 (Box 6)
    - March-April 1937, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Diaries
  Mrs. Gomon began keeping a diary in 1913. While its quality varies from year to year, she continued it without interruption for almost 60 years. The diaries offer insight both into her character and the events in which she was involved.
  - 1912 (Box 6)
  - 1913, 2 volumes (Box 6)
  - 1914 (Box 6)
  - 1915-1916 (Box 6)
  - 1918 (Box 6)
  - 1919-1920 (Box 6)
  - 1922 (Box 6)
  - 1925 (comments concerning Clarence Darrow) (Box 6)
  - 1925 (concerning Sweet case) (Box 6)
  - 1925 (Women's Campaign Committee) (Box 6)
  - October 1925-November 1932, 11 folders (Box 6)
    (lacking January 1928-December 1929)
  - May 1932-1973, 40 folders (Box 7)
    (lacking 1928-1929, January-February 1932, June-July 1932, November 1953)
  - 1974, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/Personal series concerns awards and honors received, speeches given, miscellaneous writings, and family matters.
  - Awards and Citations (Box 8)
  - Funeral guest register November 1975 (Box 8)
  - Gomon Political campaign materials (Box 8)
  - Gomon Marriage certificate (Box 8)
  - Fellows family of Ann Arbor (Box 8)
  - Interview (UM-WSU Institute for Labor and Industrial Relations) 1959 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame 1983 (includes photographs) (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 8)
  - Notebooks of reviews of books, 3 items (Box 8)
  - Notebooks of miscellaneous materials, especially writings and random thoughts, 14 items (Box 8)
  - Speech to the Michigan ACLU Sixth Annual Dinner 1968 (Box 8)
  - Wayne State Univ. Honorary Degree 1961
    - Program and Degree (Box 8)
      (includes photograph)
    - Congratulatory Correspondence (Box 8)
  - Writings
    - Detroit (Box 8)
    - Ford (Box 8)
    - Lodge, John C. (Box 8)
    - Murphy, Frank miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous writings (Box 8)
- Materials concerning Frank Murphy
  Mrs. Gomon accumulated significant primary material from her association with Frank Murphy. This includes speeches of Frank Murphy, clippings about him, and other materials. Also included in this series is a group of nine intimate letters (1932-1933) addressed to Murphy from Louise Victoria (surname unknown). These letters had been torn in small pieces by someone and saved by Gomon. They were reconstructed by Bentley Library conservation staff in 2013.
  - Speeches August 1930-November 1932 (Box 8)
  - Speeches undated, mayoral, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Speeches undated, mayoral, 8 folders (Box 9)
  - Materials 1931 Mayor's Unemployment Committee (Box 9)
  - Materials 1932 United States Conference of Mayors in Detroit
    - Proceedings (Box 9)
    - Correspondence (Box 9)
  - Materials 1933 Report into Causes of Strike at Briggs Manufacturing Co. (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous papers regarding Mayoralty (Box 9)
  - Speeches 1933-1938 (Box 9)
  - Sit-down strike 1937 (Box 9)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee hearing concerning appointment to Supreme Court (Box 9)
  - Clippings (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, reconstructed 1932-1933, 9 folders (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, unreconstructed 1932-1933 (Box 9)
- Materials related to Gomon's projected biography of Frank Murphy (never published)
  The draft of Mrs. Gomon's projected biography of Frank Murphy is also found in the collection. This work is particularly strong in its discussion of Murphy's years in Detroit and his term of office as governor of Michigan.
  - Correspondence from Curtis Brown, Ltd. (publisher) (Box 9)
  - Correspondence from Murphy associates
    - April 1951 (Box 9)
    - May-November 1951 (Box 9)
    - 1952 (Box 9)
  - Outline of biography (Box 9)
  - Notes for biography, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Drafts
    - Early family history to "Big Four" Recorders' Court campaign 1924 (Box 9)
    - Ann Arbor-University of Michigan (Box 9)
    - Assistant District Attorney (Box 9)
    - Recorders Court campaign (Box 9)
    - Recorders Court campaign, Mrs. Lewen: The Twentieth Century Club (Box 9)
    - Recorders Court term: Sweet case (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous regarding city politics in Detroit before Murphy mayoralty (Box 9)
    - Mayoralty campaign (Box 9)
    - Mayoralty, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Mayoral re-election, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Mayoral Second Term (Box 10)
    - 1932 State Democratic Convention (Box 10)
    - Mayoral Second Term: Briggs Strike (Box 10)
    - City Finances (Box 10)
    - Philippines (Box 10)
    - Campaign for Governor (Box 10)
    - Governor (Box 10)
    - Governor: Sit down strike, General Motors (Box 10)
    - Governor: Sit down strike, pp.1-50 (Box 10)
    - Governor: Sit down strike, pp. 51-114 (Box 10)
    - Governor: More sit down strikes (Box 10)
    - Governor: Labor (Box 10)
    - Supreme Court appointment (Box 10)
    - Recall in Detroit (Box 10)
    - History of Michigan Politics (Box 10)
  - "What Makes Frank Murphy Tick?" (Box 10)
  - "Matters Affecting the Democrat Party in Michigan"-Peter Fogan (Box 10)
  - "Messiah or Mortal" (re: Frank Murphy)-Harry Meade (Box 10)
  - "My Friend" (Frank Murphy); Recollections regarding prohibition in Detroit (Box 10)
  - Outline of Murphy biography (Box 10)
  - "Frank Murphy and His Women" (Box 10)
  - Notes for biography, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - "Mr. Justice Murphy's Contribution to Law"-Thurgood Marshall (Box 10)
  - "Mr. Justice Murphy, Humanitarian, Administrator, Dissenting Jurist"-Hillmer Gellein (Box 10)
- Ford Motor Company materials
  Josephine Gomon also intended to publish a work about Henry Ford. It dealt with Ford during the World War II period while Mrs. Gomon was working at Willow Run. She was particularly close to Harry Bennett, and through him, Henry Ford. Her writing is particularly interesting because she is sympathetic to both Ford and Bennett.
  - Reminiscences, especially relating to Harry Bennett, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - "The Poor Mr. Ford" unpublished manuscript (Box 10)
  - "The Poor Mr. Ford" drafts, 8 folders (Box 10)
- Photographs
  The photographs include portraits of Mrs. Gomon as well as posed and un-posed photos of guests at the 1960 dinner honoring her. Also included are miscellaneous photos from Frank Murphy's career.
  - Portraits, formal and informal (Box 10)
  - Testimonial banquet December 9, 1960, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (including photo of J. Gomon with Harry Bennett) (Box 10)
  - Frank Murphy
    - As mayor of Detroit (Box 10)
    - As governor of Michigan
      - Photos relating to auto strike negotiations (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous (including photos of Frank Murphy with Father Coughlin) (Box 10)
      - Memorabilia (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous and undated (Box 10)
  - Eleanor Roosevelt visit to Detroit 1935 (Box 10)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Arnow, Harriette Louisa Simpson, 1908-1986.
June 15,1961; July 13,1961; Sept. 16,1961; Sept. 23,1961; 1962; Feb. 21,1963; June 6,1963; undated,1964; Jan. 12,1964; Aug. 8,1964; Jan. 12,1966; undated,1967; Feb.,1967; Apr. 4,1967; Nov. 18,1967; undated,1968; Aug. 3,1968.
Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1889-1968
Sept. 2, 1963.
Bowles, George Edward, 1915-
Feb. 1, 1962; Jan. 27, 1968; May 2, 1968.
Brickley, James, 1927-
Jan. 18, 1965; Feb. 4, 1965; Jan. 21, 1970.
Bumgardner, Eleanor M. (Eleanor Margaret)
Dec. 2, 1969.
Carey, Ed.
Feb. 18, 1964; Mar. 30, 1964.
Cavanagh, Jerome Patrick, 1928-1979.
Feb. 21,1964; Sept. 15,1964; Jan. 6,1965; June 22,1965; Aug. 18,1965; June 10,1966; Jan. 24,1967; Aug. 16,1967; Apr. 19,1968; May 9,1968; May 17,1968; May 29,1968; May 9,1969; Nov. 6,1969; Apr. 9,1973.
Darrow, Ruby
Nov. 29, 1929.
Downs, Tom, 1916-
Sept. 7, 1964; Sept. 18, 1964; Oct. 4, 1964; Nov. 5, 1966.
Edwards, George, 1914-
Mar. 29, 1964; Dec. 8, 1972.
Ferency, Zolton A., 1922-
Feb. 24, 1964; Apr. 14, 1970; June 11, 1970.
FitzGerald, Frank
Apr. 14, 1959.
Girardin, Ray, d. 1971.
Jan. 21, 1963; Oct. 7, 1964; Dec. 7, 1964; Oct. 17, 1967.
Griffin, Robert P. (Robert Paul), 1923-
Sept. 30, 1968; Feb. 25, 1970; Apr. 13, 1970; Sept. 28,1973.
Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.
1963; Feb. 11,1964; Feb. 26,1964; May 29,1964; Feb. 12,1965; Apr. 2,1965; May 12,1967; Sept. 30,1968; Apr. 25,1968; June 25,1968; Aug. 3,1971; Sept. 24,1974.
Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.
Aug. 20, 1963; May 19, 1964.
Knight, John Shively, 1894-1981.
July 30,1965; Nov. 24,1965; Dec. 31,1965; Sept. 9,1966; Oct. 24,1966; Nov. 10,1966; May 1,1967; July 8,1974; Mar. 13,1975.
McNamara, Patrick Vincent, 1894-1966
Nov. 29, 1963; Apr. 5, 1965; July 7, 1965; Nov. 16, 1965.
Milliken, William G., 1922-
Aug. 19, 1971; Feb. 10, 1971; Mar. 21, 1972; Nov. 28, 1972; Sept. 11, 1974.
Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949
Apr. 25,1929; Apr. 24,1933; Apr. 26,1933; May 6,1935; Aug. 5,1935; June 18,1936; July 14,1937; May 17,1937; May 28,1937; June 2,1937; Nov. 3,1937; Mar. 3,1938; Aug. 27,1941; Apr. 24,1948; Dec. 25,1948; June 6,1949.
Murphy, George, 1897-1961
Jan. 17, 1955; Jan. 8, 1959; Feb. 6, 1959; Apr. 3, 1959.
Ravitz, Mel, 1924-
Apr. 14, 1964; May 19, 1964; Feb. 6, 1967; Nov. 23, 1970; Dec. 11, 1970; July 8, 1970; Apr. 13, 1971.
Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.
June 20, 1960.
Riegle, Donald W., 1938-
July 19, 1971; May 21, 1971; Dec. 23,1972.
Romney, George W., 1907-1995.
Dec. 11,1959; Nov. 3,1961; Nov. 17,1961; Dec. 29,1961; Feb. 19,1962; July 9,1963; Nov. 1,1963; Mar. 23,1964; Aug. 14,1964; June 2,1965; Aug. 27,1965; Sept. 2,1965; July 27,1966; Oct. 11,1966; Apr. 10,1967; Aug. 19,1968; Jan. 3,1973.
Romney, Lenore LaFount.
May 4, 1970; Nov. 14, 1970; Sept. 10, 1972.
Souris, Theodore, 1925-
June 27,1960; Dec. 3,1960; Nov. 15,1961; Oct. 26,1964; Dec. 9,1964; Apr. 15,1968.
Staebler, Neil, 1905-
May 6, 1963; Mar. 5, 1964.
Sugar, Maurice, 1891-1974
Jan. 15, 1970.
Taylor, Hobart, 1920-1981.
Jan. 21, 1965.
Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Nov. 6, 1963.
Woodcock, Leonard.
Dec. 1, 1970; Feb. 25, 1975.